听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
我们前面已经学习了网站这一分布式系统实例
So, we saw the web as one example of a distributed system
此分布式系统包含客户端和服务端
consisting of a client and a server.
我们来看另一个实例
Let's look at another practical example,
想象一下 你在使用某个在线商店购买一些东西
which is imagine you're using some online shop to buy something.
你想要做的是
And so, what you want to do is
当选择好自己要买的商品后
you want to enter your credit card number on this shop
你将在商店里输入自己的信用卡号
after you've chosen the stuff you want to buy.
随后 你结算账单 使用信用卡支付费用
And then, you check out, and you pay with your credit card.
支付费用后 商品就会寄送到你这里
And then, you get the goods shipped to you.
这一过程所发生的事情是
So, what happens here is that
实际处理信用卡支付过程的支付服务
the payment service that actually processes this credit card payment
一般都是由另一个不同的公司来提供的
is usually provided by a different company
支付服务一般不会由运行在线商店的公司来提供
from the company that is running the online shop,
因为处理信用卡支付属于非常专业的操作
because processing credit card payments is a very specialized activity,
更合理的做法是
so, it makes sense that
一些公司专门处理信用卡支付过程
they're companies that specialize in just doing credit card payments,
其他公司
and another company
专门负责提供在线商店、供货等服务
specializes in actually providing the shop and the goods and so on.
当你在某个在线商店输入你的信用卡号后
So, what happens when you enter your credit card number on some online shop is that
在线商店将向支付服务发送一条消息
the online shop will send a message to this payment service,
而支付服务运行在另一个公司所提供的节点上
which is running on a different node provided by a different company.
这条消息将包含你的信用卡号
And this message will contain the details of your card number,
需要此信用卡支付的金额
and how much they want to charge to that card,
以及很多其他的信息 例如你的账单地址等等
and various other information, maybe your billing address, and so on.
这些信息将会被发送给支付服务
This will get sent to the payment service.
支付服务将完成一系列复杂的处理过程
The payment service then does a whole lot of complicated stuff.
它们与Visa或MasterCard等信用卡支付网络通信
They talk to the card payment network such as Visa or MasterCard.
信用卡支付网络将与银行通信 确认这张信用卡确实是此银行分发的
The card payment network then talks to the bank that issued your card.
银行需要确定你的账户上的确有钱
They make sure that you actually have money in your account,
随后 银行要保证支付可以顺利完成
and then, they make sure that the payment can be taken.
如果支付成功 它们将按照相反的顺序再返回支付结果
And if it's successful, then they go through all of this in reverse.
这中间可能会涉及额外的检查操作
And maybe they do extra checks to
例如你需要输入口令 或者服务需要向你发送验证消息等等
like make you enter a password, or send you a test message, or whatever it might be.
所有这些过程结束后
And eventually, hopefully,
支付服务向在线商店发送回一条消息
the payment service then sends a message back to the online shop
表示支付是否成功完成
indicating whether the payment was successful or not.
这是一个非常具体的分布式系统实例
And so, this is very concrete example of a distributed system
在线商店每天都会执行上述流程
that is really used like this every single day.
我们来简单看看具体代码长什么样子
Now, let's have a look a bit at what the code might look like.
想象你自己是在线商店的程序员
So, imagine you are one of the programmers working on the side of the online shop.
你正在开发运行在线商店的软件
So, you're developing the software that runs the online shop,
你正在撰写处理信用卡支付的代码
and you're writing the code that is supposed to handle the credit card payments
让在线商店使用支付服务完成支付
and talk to the payment service.
你写出的代码差不多应该是这个样子
And so, the code you write might look something like this here.
假设你的基础代码里包含一个card（信用卡）对象
So, let's assume that there's a card object in your code base.
你可以创建一个新的card对象实例
And you can create a new instance of this card object.
你可以向这个对象传入
And you can give it
信用卡号、有效期、以及信用卡背后的3个数字
the credit card number, and the expiry date, and the 3 digits on the back.
你可以把所有这些信息都打包到card对象中
And you can package all of this up as a card object.
随后 你将调用下面这个函数
And then, you call this function.
你有某个叫paymentService（支付服务）的对象
So, you have some object that has this paymentService.
你调用此对象的processPayment（处理支付）方法
And you call the processPayment method on this function.
你在方法中输入待付费的信用卡
And you give it the card that you want to charge.
并输入支付的金额
And you give it the amount that you want to charge it,
以及付款所用的货币类型
and the currency in which you want to charge it.
随后 你需要根据支付是否成功这一信息执行后续的操作
And then, depending on whether this is successful or not, you then fulfill the order.
了解整个过程具体发生了什么是非常有趣的一件事
So, this is quite interesting what is happening here,
仔细思考一下
because if you think about it,
支付服务运行在另一个公司提供的节点上
the payment service is running on a different node, run by a different company.
这部分代码不属于在线商店
It's not part of the code base of the online shop.
具体来说 当你调用这个processPayment函数时
So, what is happening here is when you call this processPayment function,
你的程序并未包含此函数的实现
the implementation of that function is not within your program.
具体实现在另一个节点上
The implementation is somewhere on another node
你和这个节点通过网络连接
at the other end of an internet connection.
这里实际发生的情况是
And what is actually happening here is
看起来这像是在做函数调用或方法调用
what looks like a function call or a method call.
但在背后 调用过程会被翻译成一些网络通信消息
It is actually underneath being translated into some kind of network communication.
这种调用过程称为远程过程调用
And this is called a Remote Procedure Call.
远程函数调用这个名字可能更合适
Maybe a Remote Function Call would be a better name,
但大家一般都把这个过程叫远程过程调用
but Remote Procedure Call is what this thing is typically called.
因此 我们遵从行业惯例 仍然使用这个名词
And so, we're just going to stick with that name.
Java把相同的操作称为远程方法调用
Java calls the same thing Remote Method Invocation.
这本质上给相同思想起的另一个名字
Again, just a different word for essentially the same idea.
我们来看看远程过程调用 即RPC是如何工作的
And so, let's have a look at how RPC, a Remote Procedure Call works.
RPC一般由RPC框架来实现的
So, RPC is typically implemented with something called an RPC framework,
有时我们会把RPC框架称为中间件
or it's called middleware sometimes.
RPC框架是一个软件 它实现的功能就是
This is a piece of software that performs the translation between
把你编程语言中的函数调用
the function call in your programming language
翻译为通过网络发送的消息
and this message passing over the network.
因此 当在线商店的代码调用这个processPayment函数时
And so, when the code of the online shop calls this processPayment function,
在线商店无法在另一个节点上直接调用这个函数
it can't directly call the function on a different node,
因为你的编程语言一般无法支持这种函数调用方法
because your programming language doesn't support that normally.
取代而之的是 RPC框架提供一个桩函数
Instead, the RPC framework provides what is called a stub.
桩函数拥有相同的类型签名
So, the stub function, it has the same type signature,
它看起来和你希望调用的远程节点函数完全相同
and it looks the same as the function on the remote node that you want to call.
你希望调用这个processPayment函数
So, you want to call this processPayment function.
实际上 这个桩函数不会真的处理支付过程
And what we make is this stub function that doesn't actually process the payment.
那它做了什么呢？
But what it does?
它向服务发送一条消息 服务会处理支付过程
It sends a message to the service, which then does process the payment.
在线商店将调用这个桩函数
So, the online shop calls into this stub function here.
RPC客户端需要读取传入桩函数的参数
And the RPC client needs to take the arguments that were passed to that function,
并将这些参数翻译为可以通过网络发送的消息
and translate them into a message that can be sent over the network.
这个翻译过程
And this translation process
也就是将编程语言中的参数翻译为网络通信消息的过程
from arguments in your programming language to message over the network
叫做编组
is called marshalling.
因此 编组 我也称之为编码 以函数调用参数为输入
And so, marshalling, or I call it encoding as well, takes the function arguments,
将参数编码成可以通过网络发送的消息
and encodes it in some way that can be sent over the network.
举例来说 可以把参数编码为json 这个例子里使用的就是json
So, for example, it might use json. In this example, it uses json.
也可以把参数编码为某种二进制格式
It could use some kind of binary format.
大家先不用考虑具体应该使用什么格式
The format, it doesn't really matter.
本质上 编组将参数编码为字节串
But it becomes then essentially just a sequence of bytes
我们可以把字节串放到在消息中 通过网络把参数发送出去
that we can pack into a message, send over the network.
在接收方一侧 RPC服务器将收到这条消息
And then, on the recipient side, the RPC server is going to receive this message.
并把收到的消息翻译回服务端函数调用所需的参数
And it's going to translate it back into a function call on the server side.
服务端侧
And so, here now,
包含了processPayment函数的具体实现
this is where the actual implementation of the processPayment function lives.
RPC服务端侧会调用这里实现的函数
And so, here on the RPC server side now, this function is going to get called.
此函数将完成必要的操作 处理支付流程
And it's going to do whatever is necessary in order to make this payment happen.
这可能涉及到与信用卡网络和银行通信
And that will probably involve talking to the card network, and the bank,
更新数据库中的一些数据 完成一系列其他的操作
and updating some databases, and doing a whole bunch of extra stuff.
最终 这个函数会返回处理结果
And eventually, this function will return.
我们希望这个函数可以告诉我们信用卡支付结果是成功还是失败了
And hopefully, it will tell us whether the card payment was successful or not.
我们也需要编组此函数的返回值
So, the return value of this function again needs to be marshaled.
我们要按相反的方向返回消息
We do exactly the same in reverse.
RPC服务端编组函数的返回值
So, the RPC server marshals the return value of the function,
把结果消息m_2通过网络再发送回来
sends it back as a message m_2 of the network.
RPC客户端反编组消息
The RPC client unmarshals it,
将消息转换回编程语言所用的数据类型
and turns it back into the data types of the programming language that you're using.
最终 函数成功返回结果
And then, eventually, the function returns.
因此 我们实现的效果是
And so, what we've done now is
假装我们是在本地调用的函数
to kind of pretend what we're doing is calling a function locally,
但实际上 背后发生的事情是
but actually, what's happening underneath is
参数以消息的形式发送给了另一个服务
this communication via messages to another service.
我们希望实现的理想效果是
So, the ideal that we kind of want here is that
向其他服务执行函数调用看起来就像本地调用一样
the function call to a different service looks just like a local function call,
因为我们知道如何用我们使用的编程语言调用这个函数
because we know what functions in our programming language look like,
我们希望远程RPC有相同的函数调用方法
we would quite like the remote RPC to look just like that.
这一原则叫位置透明性
And this principle is called location transparency.
也就是说 所调用资源的位置
So, the location of where your resource is located
也就是你调用processPayment时所用的对象
that is, whether the objects that you're calling your processPayment on
无论是在你的本地地址空间上处理这个对象
whether that's an object in your own process in your local address space
还是在互联网连接的另一端处理这个对象
or whether it's somewhere on the other end of an internet connection,
我们希望处理位置是透明的
we want that to be transparent.
我们不想让调用方觉得不同位置的调用方法不一样
We want not to be able to tell the difference between the two.
然而 现实总不会那么简单
However, actually reality doesn't look that simple,
因为我在最开始已经提到过 麻烦在于网络可能会出现故障
Because, as I said in the beginning, the trouble with networks is that they can fail.
有可能发生的是 你向网络发送一条消息 但消息没有到达目的地
So, it can be that you send a message over the network, and the message does not arrive.
你当然可以重新发送此消息
You could send it again, of course,
但如果是这样 我们要多次用这个信用卡支付相同的账单吗？
but then, are you going to charge the credit card multiple times?
当我们想重复发送消息时 处理时要特别小心
We have to be quite careful if we're going to send messages again.
消息可能会丢失 那我们该如何实现重试操作呢？
So, messages might be lost. What do we do about retry?
消息接收也会出现延迟问题
Messages also might be delayed.
有可能发生的是 消息确实成功发送到了对方手中
So, it might be that the message did actually get through,
但可能因为某些原因使得网络出现了抖动
but for some reason, there was some networking hiccups somewhere
这使得消息接收出现了延时
that caused the message to be delayed by a while.
这种情况也有可能发生
That could happen as well.
还有可能发生的事情是 处理这个函数的服务
It could also happen that the service that is processing this function
在函数处理的过程中崩溃了
crashed in the middle of executing our function,
这时 服务就不能返回响应消息了
in that case, it won't be able to send us back a response.
但处理函数可能部分处理了我们的请求
But it might have partially processed our request.
我猜这里我们可以使用事务来解决这个问题
I guess we can use transactions here, and said, yes, OK.
可以看到 远程调用会面临很多的问题
You can see there are a lot of open questions here.
根本上看
And fundamentally,
向远程资源执行函数调用
it seems like actually making a function call to a remote resource
与调用本地函数所面临的情况是完全不同的
is something totally different from calling a local function.
这完全是两种不同的情况
They're simply two different things.
我们可以让这两种调用方法看起来相似
We can make them look somewhat similar,
我们可以给函数设置相似的函数类型签名
we can give the functions a similar type signature,
但调用远程函数会遇到上述一系列可能发生的错误情况
but calling a remote function has all of these error cases
而本地调用时不会发生类似的错误
that simply don't arise in local execution.
这些问题未能阻止人们花费海量的时间尝试构建RPC框架
But that hasn't stopped people from trying to build RPC frameworks over a long time
即使确实在调用另一个节点上的服务
that try to look like you're calling a local function
人们也在尝试让远程调用看起来和本地调用很相似
even though you're calling something on another node.
回到二十世纪八十年代 那时候人们就创造出了RPC这个术语
So, it started right back in the 1980s when the term RPC was first coined,
一些微型系统开始使用RPC
and like some microsystems had this thing.
用于构建NFS 即网络文件系统
And it was used to build NFS, the network file system
我们将在本课程将会讲解相关技术
of which we'll see more later in the course.
二十世纪九十年代出现了一个非常热的领域
And then, in the 1990s, this was a very hot topic.
人们开始讨论面向对象中间件
People then talked about object-oriented middleware.
那时候出现的CORBA（公共对象请求代理体系结构）势头火热
And there was this thing called CORBA, which was like really hot.
不过 现在已经没有人用CORBA了
Nowadays, nobody uses it anymore.
随后 出现了一系列竞争技术
Then, there were a whole bunch of competing technologies,
例如 Java的远程方法调用和CORBA比较类似
like Java's Remote Method Invocation is kind of a similar type to CORBA.
我们不会介绍这些技术的细节
We won't go into the details of all of these.
我只是在这里提一下这些技术的名字 因为大家后续可能会遇到这些名字
I'm just mentioning the names here, because you might encounter them in your careers.
因此 至少可以提前接触一下这些技术的名字
And so, it's good to at least have seen them before.
2015年 也就是最近 谷歌公布了另一个RPC框架
And just as recently as 2015, Google brought out another RPC framework.
称为gRPC 意思是谷歌的RPC
It's called gRPC，for Google's RPC.
这是个不错的RPC 如果你想用RPC 可以试试这个框架
It's fine. If you want to do RPC, why not? You can use it.
你也可以用其他的框架 也没什么问题
You can use something else. It doesn't really matter.
现在非常常见的是所谓的REST
What is very common nowadays is actually something called REST.
意思是表述性状态转移 这个名字有点拗口
This stands for REpresentational State Transfer, a bit of a mouthful.
REST实际上是如何使用HTTP的一系列法则
But it's really a set of principles for how to use HTTP.
REST的狂热爱好者们不喜欢把REST看成一种RPC
People who are keen enthusiasts of REST don't like to think of REST as RPC.
他们喜欢把REST和RPC看成两种哲学
They like to think of REST and RPC as two different philosophies.
但本质上 它们是一回事
But essentially, they're the same kind of thing.
本质上 它们实现的功能仍然是
So, essentially, they're still about
调用代码 以发起网络请求的方式
invoking code and causing something to happen in a remote service
让远程服务完成一些处理工作
by making some network requests to it,
在你的编程语言下 以某种合理的方式
and packaging the whole thing up
把所有的信息打包在一起
in some reasonably nice way in your programming language.
用RESTful方法构建RPC的方式非常流行的原因是
So, one reason why this RESTful approach of building RPC became so popular
网页浏览器支持构建HTTP请求
was that web browsers support making HTTP requests.
因此 你可以利用到一些运行在网页浏览器的JavaScript代码
So, you can have some JavaScript code running within a web browser.
这些代码可以构建发送给服务器的HTTP请求
And this code can make HTTP requests to a server.
这些代码可以构造出任何想在请求中发送的数据 把数据发出去
And it can construct whatever data it wants to send in that request, send it out,
也可以接收到从服务端发送回的响应
and it can receive the response back from the server.
有时也把这个技术称为Ajax
This technique is sometimes also called Ajax.
实现上述过程的代码看起来像这个样子
And it looks something like this.
如果我想用JavaScript实现信用卡支付的例子
So, if I want to implement this credit card payment example in JavaScript,
我首先要创建这个args对象
I might first of all create this object args
对象中包含了RPC函数调用所需的参数
containing the arguments to the function call for the RPC.
这个对象将包含金额、货币类型
So, that will contain the amount, and the currency
信用卡号、支付地址等信息
and the card number, and the billing address, and so on.
随后 我要构建request对象
And then, I construct this request object,
这个对象明确了我想使用哪种HTTP方法
which says which HTTP method I want to use.
POST方法一般用于提交一个表格
So, POST is the method that's used for submitting forms usually
当你想修改服务器的某些状态时 一般会使用POST方法
when you're changing some state on the server.
得到这些参数后
I'm now going to take the arguments,
我将使用json.stringify函数将它们转换为json字符串
and turn them into a json string using the json.stringify function.
我可以告诉服务端 我提交的是json格式的数据
And I can tell the server that json is the type of data that I'm providing.
我本质上是在告诉服务端提交的文件格式
So, I'm providing the file type essentially.
随后 我调用这个URL
And then, I can call this URL,
意思是向example.com/payments这个URL发送一个HTTP请求
which means actually sending an HTTP request to this URL example.com/payments
请求中包含了上述所有参数
with all of the details specified above.
接下来 我得到了下面两个处理程序
And then, we have these two handlers down here.
then分支包含了一个回调函数
So, the then case has a function call back here,
如果此网络请求得到了一个表示成功的响应 就会调用此回调函数
which gets called if that network request resulted as in a successful response.
如果我们从服务端得到了一个返回的响应
So, if we got a response back from the server,
那么这里的response变量就表示具体的响应是什么
then this variable response here becomes that response.
此时 我们执行这里的代码
And then, we execute this code here.
我们现在可以查看从服务端得到的响应
So, we can now look at the response that we got from the server
查看服务端回复的状态码 判断请求是成功了还是失败了
and see whether the status code that it replies indicates success or not.
如果状态码表示请求成功 这意味着响应大概率也是json格式的
So, if it indicates success, that means the response is probably json again.
我们可以调用这个json函数 将响应反编组为JavaScript对象
So, we can unmarshal that back into objects in JavaScript by calling this json function,
随后 调用success函数
and then, call the success function
表示我们从服务端得到了一个表示调用成功的状态
to indicate that we got a successful status back from the server.
否则 如果状态码的意思是未能成功
Otherwise, if the status code was not success,
我们就以状态码为输入来调用failure函数
then we could call a failure function with the status code, for example.
当然了 我们可以更细节地处理相应的错误 但基本实现思想是这样的
Of course, we can do more detailed error handling, but that's just the general idea.
这是我们从服务端收到了响应时的处理过程
So, this is the case where we got a response back from the server.
当然了 消息可能会丢失
Now, of course, messages can be lost.
因此 可能出现我们没有收到服务端响应的情况
And so, it might be that we don't get a response back from the server.
遇到这种情况时 举例来说 请求可以简单地等待30秒
And in this case, for example, the request might just wait for 30 seconds.
如果30秒内没有收到任何响应
And if it doesn't receive anything within 30 seconds,
我们会说 超时了 我们放弃了
it's going to say, timeout, we give up.
请求消息可能发送成功了 也可能没发送成功 我们也不知道发生了什么
The message might have got through or might not, we don't really know.
但我们会给你一个网络错误
But we're going to give you a network error.
这部分代码处理的就是这种情况
And that's what happens here.
catch分支内 我们有另一个回调函数
So, in this catch case here, we have another callback function
如果网络请求未能从服务端收到响应 就会进入到catch分支
which gets called if the network request did not result in a response from the server.
这种情况下 我们也会调用failure函数 并把错误信息传进去
And in that case, I'm just going to call that failure function again and pass the error in.
实际中 你可能希望
In practice, you would probably want to
给用户展示一条消息 向用户解释可能出现了一些错误
show the user a message and explain that something went wrong.
这就是RPC的基本使用方法
Anyway, so, this is the basics of how you would do RPC.
这就是如何应用JavaScript 即通过HTTP协议使用REST API
And this is how you would use a REST API over HTTP in JavaScript.
我前面也说过 这种网页浏览器应用范式非常流行
And this pattern has become very popular, as I said, for web browsers.
很多网站都使用此类技术
And most websites now will use this kind of technique
在不需要重载整个页面 就可以构建HTTP请求
to make HTTP requests to the server without reloading the whole page.
我们只是在网页浏览器里运行JavaScript
And so, it's just JavaScript running in your web browser
让网页浏览器像客户端应用那样构建并发送网络请求
that acts like a client-side program, which is performing these network requests.
服务端与服务端通信的场景会用到与之非常相似的技术
But the very similar techniques are also used for server-to-server communication.
这个技术在大公司里特别受欢迎
And so, this technique is particularly popular in large companies.
在大型企业中 我们有很多巨大的软件系统
So, in large enterprises, you have these huge software systems,
它们在执行公司运转所需的各种操作
which are running all of the operations of the company.
这些软件系统非常庞大、非常复杂
And these software systems are far too big and far too complex
单台计算机上运行的程序完全无法支撑这样复杂的软件
to have just like a single program running on one computer.
只是因为程序过于复杂
So, simply because of the sheer complexity,
有时也因为这些系统要处理的数据过于庞大
sometimes also because the large amounts of data that these things have to process,
企业才必须使用分布式系统
they are distributed systems.
为此 我们要在多台计算机上运行多个节点
So, you have multiple nodes running on multiple computers
所有节点为大型组织提供基础设施服务
which are all providing part of the infrastructure of this large organization.
大型组织可以是银行、零售商等
It might be a bank, or a retailer, or whatever.
这一系列大型软件会被拆分为所谓的服务
And this large bunch of software is broken up into what are called services,
将大型软件拆分为服务的方法
and an approach where you break down a large piece of software into services
称为面向服务的体系结构
is called a service-oriented architecture,
一个时髦的术语是微服务
or a more modern term is to call it microservices.
拆分的目的只是让程序运行在多个节点上
And this is just having programs running on different nodes
并允许它们通过RPC通信
which communicate via RPC.
RPC在此场景下提供了关键机制
And so, RPC here is the key mechanism
允许这些软件可以相互通信
that allows these bits of software to interact with each other.
我后面会稍微介绍一下这类场景下是如何使用RPC的
And so, I'll tell you a little bit more about RPC in these kinds of settings.
我们已经见过网页浏览器了
So, we've seen it in the web browser.
但这里是面向服务的体系结构
But here, in service-oriented architecture,
我们这里所说的服务一般都是在数据中心内运行的
you're normally talking about services that are running within a data center.
它们可能在相同数据中心内的多个不同的节点上运行
And so, they might be running on multiple different servers in the same data center.
一般来说 所有这些服务都依靠数据中心的网络通信
But generally, they are all services talking over the data center network.
这些服务并不在用户终端设备上运行
So, these are not services running on your end user device,
不在你的手机、笔记本电脑上运行
like your phone or your laptop,
它们是数据中心侧的服务
but they are data center site services.
不过 RPC的使用过程不变
But we can use RPC equally well regardless of
无论是终端用户与服务端通信 还是服务端与服务端通信 使用过程是一致的
whether it's like end user devices talking to a server or servers talking to other servers.
这些大型企业系统中的软件会存在一个问题
What you do get in these large-scale enterprise systems is that
软件会使用一大堆不同的编程语言开发
they use a whole bunch of different programming languages,
因为内部可能会有一些旧系统
because they have some old systems,
有些旧系统可能是用COBOL写的
they might have some old systems written in COBOL,
稍微新一点的系统可能是用C++写的
then they'll have some slightly newer systems written in C++,
新开发的一些系统可能使用Java写的
and have a bit newer systems written in Java,
还有很多最新开发的一些系统
and then they'll have the latest systems
它们可能是用当前最流行的编程语言开发的
in whatever is the latest most fashionable programming language right now.
这些系统需要相互通信
And these systems need to talk to each other.
因此 RPC可以提供一种机制
And so, RPC can actually provide a mechanism
允许由不同编程语言实现的系统进行交互
for interoperability between these systems written in different programming languages.
这意味着 如果函数调用方和函数被调用方的代码
Now, this does mean that if the function caller and the code being called,
是用不同的编程语言实现的
if they're written in different programming languages,
你就需要保证函数的类型签名是互相匹配的
you now have to make sure that the type signatures will match up somehow.
为此 你需要进行一些数据类型转换操作
And so, you have to perform some data type conversion.
实现这一功能的方法一般是使用
And so, this is often implemented using something called
接口定义语言（IDL）
interface definition language, or an IDL,
接口定义语言本质上是描述调用函数类型签名的一种语言
which is essentially a language for specifying the type signature or function calls
使类型签名的描述方法与具体的编程语言无关
in a way that is not specific to any one programming language.
这里给出了IDL的一个例子
So, here's one example of what an IDL looks like.
这个例子来自于gRPC 也就是谷歌的RPC框架
This example is taken from gRPC, the google RPC framework.
这里使用的IDL叫Protocol Buffers
It uses an IDL called Protocol Buffers.
具体细节并不重要
The details are not important.
我只是想让大家看看IDL长什么样子
I just want to give you a bit of a flavor for what this looks like.
大家可以看到 我们在这个例子中定义了一系列不同的消息
And so, what you have here is you can have a specification of a message type.
我们定义了支付请求消息和支付状态消息
So, we can have a payment request message and a payment status message.
这是两种不同的消息类型
Those are two different messages type.
我们在下面这里定义了服务
And then, down here, we have the specification of a service.
PaymentService是一个RPC 提供了一个RPC函数调用
So, the PaymentService has an RPC, offers an RPC function call
函数名是ProcessPayment
which is called ProcessPayment.
此函数以PaymentRequest为输入 返回值的类型为PaymentStatus
It takes as argument a PaymentRequest, and it returns as its return value PaymentStatus.
上面这里 我们描述了PaymentRequest所包含的内容
And then, up here, we can say what does a PaymentRequest consist of.
PaymentRequest请求由card、amount和currency组成
Well, a PaymentRequest consists of a card, an amount, and a currency.
Card中包含一个信用卡号（cardNumber）
And the card in turn consists of a card number (cardNumber),
有效期（expiryMonth和expiryYear）
and expiry date (expiryMonth, expiryYear),
以及卡背后的3个数字（CVC）
and the 3 digits (CVC)on the back.
currency是一个枚举（enum）类型 标识了所有可能的取值
And the currency might be an enum, indicating the possible values.
忽略这里的1、2、3、4
Ignore those 1, 2, 3, 4 values here.
为什么这里要使用这些数字与本课程的内容关系不大
And the details of that are not important for the purposes of this course.
但大家可以看到 我使用了一些数据类型
But you can see here I'm using data types
这里的int32表示这是一个32比特有符号整数
like int32 to indicate this is a 32-bit signed integer.
这些是非常通用的数据类型
And that is like a fairly generic data type
你可以认为大多数编程语言都支持这些数据类型
that you would expect most programming languages to support that kind of thing.
类似地 字符串（string）是一种非常常见的数据类型
Likewise, here, string data type is very common.
对于枚举类型（enum） 如果编程语言不支持枚举类型
An enum, if the language doesn't support enum,
你可以把枚举类型转换为整数或者其他数据类型
you could translate it into just an integer or something like that.
布尔（bool）也是一个非常常见的数据类型
Boolean (bool) again is a common data type.
你可以争论到 cardNumber应该使用string类型
So, you can argue should the cardNumber be a string
还是应该使用能容纳足够数字（如容纳16个数字）的整数类型
or should be an integer with sufficient digits that you can have, 16 digits.
我们可以讨论这个问题 但这里的目的是让大家了解一般性规则
Whatever, we can argue about that, but you get the general principle.
这是一个与编程语言无关的RPC格式规范
This is a language independent specification of what the RPC can look like.
可以为RPC框架配置IDL 配置格式规范
And the RPC framework can take this IDL, can take a specification,
它就可以根据格式规范为你喜欢的任何编程语言生成代码
and generate code in all of your favorite programming languages.
基于此
And so, that way, then,
RPC框架就可以为RPC客户端和RPC服务端生成桩函数
it can generate the stubs for both the RPC client and the RPC server
让我们很方便地为调用方和服务端被调用方
that make it easy to write code that performs the RPC
撰写执行RPC的代码
on both the caller side and the side of the service that's being called.
这就是RPC
So, that's RPC.
接下来 我们将稍微讨论
Next time, we will talk a bit more about
实现可靠分布式系统时所需面对的关键问题
the fundamental issues of actually making reliable distributed systems.